[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha often compared the sense fields with the ocean and the dangerous creatures living in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was wondering if you could shed some light on that analogy, since I myself can't really make much sense of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: The ocean stands for something whose depth or whose extent you cannot fathom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only guess how far it goes and what things it can contain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same way, you have no way to anticipate how much your senses can pressure you.
[SPEAKER_01]: How much... how many different significances they can try to overwhelm you with.
[SPEAKER_01]: How many sights, sounds, smells, tastes and touches can strike those senses?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same way, it's the...
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same way as you couldn't possibly deal with the ocean, because, again, you don't know the extent of it, you couldn't deal with it fully by taking all of the individual things and having countermeasures against them, you need to
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be prepared for anything that might come within the ocean.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same way, you need to be prepared for anything that could come within your six sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how coarse, how subtle, how pleasant, unpleasant, how familiar or unfamiliar.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of it has to be included in the same training, and all of it has to be permeated by the same immovability.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, oftentimes, people overlook that, of course, because their practice revolves around
[SPEAKER_01]: Dealing with specific things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, whatever person that upsets them or situation that's challenging them, they will try to do these kind of reframing techniques that sometimes are presented as meta or whatever, even though they're not, to sort of
[SPEAKER_01]: Tackle those specific situations, those specific people, and not suffer on account of them anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why that approach can never...
[SPEAKER_01]: The simile of the ocean shows you why that approach can never work.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can never contribute to actual liberation, because what does it matter if you learn how to deal with crocodiles, if the sharks can still get you?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's always going to be a different type of challenging experience that you've never seen before, that you have no means to reframe in that way, and then craving will arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will get overwhelmed in that situation, because you didn't develop yourself in regard to the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, you can only experience one thing at a time, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can't simultaneously experience everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if your whole life, you will not have experienced anything that you... that was possible to experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you certainly can hold yourself back from being concerned with these specifics.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, noticing this inherent uncertainty,
[SPEAKER_01]: First of all, that exists in regard to your sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I don't know what I could be hid with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maintain that recognition, so that you don't get bogged down on any specific sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, see, that already arouses a sense of... a certain pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that keeps you on guard.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that, when there isn't anything acutely pressuring you, with the six sense bases, you still know this whole domain,
[SPEAKER_01]: In itself, is liable to attack in a way that I can't even...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't even anticipate, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that recognition, letting that sink in, is how you train yourself in regard to the whole extent of it, so that nothing then that could come through there would be a surprise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, what people would usually do is, if what's currently present is not unpleasant enough, if it's fine, then that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you let your guard down and you just rest in that until something comes up and then you're overwhelmed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it... that also is another way of saying that is not finding safety in whatever current circumstance of your experience, because that's what the six sense bases are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever current circumstance of your experience you find yourself in,
[SPEAKER_01]: You remember, this whole domain has sharks, monsters, crocodiles.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might... they may not be here right now, but it's similar to, you know, you... you... when you're floating in the ocean, it's not like the sharks come for you immediately, but they could.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: Maintaining that recognition, then, is training you, training your mind, to give up that passion that it has for these six sense bases, that it sees them as a place for getting pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, you know, there is some pleasure to be found, and the reason why people are infatuated with it is because they don't see it also comes with all these threats.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you can't divorce from the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply by being in the water, those threats are also possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a... it's a simile that, you know, yeah, that the whole... the sutta as a whole, I think, is quite often overlooked.
[SPEAKER_01]: Also, the way it says that the way you cross over the ocean or you liberate yourself, essentially, is to withstand the tides.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when it says the the eyes, the ear, the nose, their tides is sights, sounds, smells, tastes and touches.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, withstanding those tides is how you free yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically saying you can't change the fact that certain sights or sounds or sense objects have a force, let's say, or a pressure that they exert.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, that's something that people would usually be trying to deal with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Prevent those pressures from arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is not that pressure arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is when you haven't trained yourself, you haven't trained your mind, as I described before, to see those six sense bases for what they are as a not something to rest on, not something to feel that you can feel that you can be safe by manipulating it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can't withstand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when those things come up, when when certain... that force of certain sense objects come up... comes up, immediately, you are pulled to the prospect of doing something about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's pleasure chasing after it, displeasure pushing it away.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you fail to withstand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the tide will still be there when you train yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you have trained yourself, the tide will still be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, this impulse to deal with the... well, go towards the pleasure or deal with the pain, get rid of it, basically, that's what fades.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not the tide that goes away.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your response to it that came from not being able to withstand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what subsides.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not a decision that you just... because it could sound like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, you just make this firm determination to stand still.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no.
[SPEAKER_01]: That comes from an understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: It comes from understanding those six sense bases as not a basis for safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you understand it that way, then, like, you basically realize, however safe or however comfortable I can make this in the moment,
[SPEAKER_01]: There are still all these threats waiting for me that might come at any time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, how could you possibly have an impulse to kind of... or following a promise that, like, you might be able to sort it out and make it fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just give up on that whole project.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the liberation.